Guide to the Alfredo A. Roggiano Papers, 1938-1991 UA.90.F44
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Alfredo A. Roggiano Papers
1938-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Roggiano, Alfredo A.
UA.90.F44
5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Alfredo A. Roggiano was professor of Hispanic languages and literatures at the University of Pittsburgh from 1963 until 1984. In addition to his tenure as professor, Roggiano was also a renowned Argentine poet and Director of the Revista Iberoamericana, a leading scholarly journal of Latin American literature. Through his influence, the International Institute of Iberoamerican Literature has been housed at the University of Pittsburgh. Professor Roggiano's collection includes professional correspondences, various newspaper articles detailing his accomplishments, manuscripts, books, published articles, and various conferences and lectures. Many of the conferences contain records and activities of the International Institute of Iberoamerican Literature.
Biography
Alfredo A. Roggiano was an Argentine poet and distinguished professor emeritus of Hispanic languages and literatures at the University of Pittsburgh. He was born in Chivilcoy, Province of Buenos Aires, Argentina, in 1919. Roggiano died on October 27, 1991 at his home in Pittsburgh, Pa. He was seventy-two years old. Roggiano's academic and professional career spanned close to five decades. He completed his doctorate in literatures in 1945 at the University of Buenos Aires and continued postdoctoral work in the Consejo Superior de Investigaciones in Madrid, Spain. He taught at the University of Tucuman, Argentina prior to emigrating to the United States. At the University of Tucuman he served as a professor of poetics and stylistics and director of the Hispanic section of the Department of Languages and Literatures. In 1955 in protest of the Peron regime, Roggiano left his native country for the states. Before joining the University of Pittsburgh faculty, he also taught at a number of universities including the University of New Mexico, the University of California at Berkeley, and Iowa State University. Since 1955 Roggiano had also been Director of the Revista Iberoamericana, a leading scholarly journal of Latin American literature founded in Mexico City in 1938. Roggiano accepted the directorship of the journal at the Congress of the Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana celebrated at the University of California, Berkeley in 1955. That same year he was appointed Executive Director of the International Institute of Iberoamerican Literature at the age of 36. For his work with the journal, he was awarded an honorary doctorate from the National Autonomous University of Mexico in 1988. In 1963, Roggiano joined the University of Pittsburgh faculty. It was at this time that he also founded the Latin American literature program in the Department of Hispanic Languages and Literatures, retiring from that department in 1984. Over the course of his career, Roggiano authored numerous books and over seventy articles on Latin American literature. Through Roggiano's influence, the International Institute of Iberoamerican Literature has been housed at the University of Pittsburgh. Among its publications is the Revista Iberoamericana as well as a number of book series related to Iberoamerican literature including Biblioteca de América, Actas, Serie Críticas, Serie Nuevo Siglo, Serie Tres Ríos, and Serie ACP. Prior to his death, Roggiano donated $150,000 to the University of Pittsburgh to establish an endowed lecture fund in his name in the Hispanic department. The Alfredo A. Roggiano Fund supported an annual lecture series, symposia, colloquia and resulting publications on various topics. In addition, the Alfredo A. Roggiano Prize was established and awarded annually to an outstanding graduate student in the Hispanic department. His death was preceded by the publication of Prision o Transparencia, a volume containing almost all the poetry he had written over his lifetime. The slim volume has been described as a metaphysical expression to transcend the author's soul and give of himself and his experiences a form of liberation from the prison of the self.
Previous Citation
Alfredo A. Roggiano Papers, UA.90.F44, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The Alfredo A. Roggiano collection contains five series described and arranged chronologically by date. The series reflect Roggiano's many professional achievements as a professor, writer, poet, and avid lecturer. The five series include Conferences, Lectures, and Symposiums, Professional Appointments and Activities, Published and Unpublished Works, Correspondences, and Research Materials and Miscellaneous.
Separated Material
Photographs were removed to the Roggiano Personal File; Pitt Stadium dedication medal and ribbon removed to Museum Cabinet.
University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Lectures; Correspondence; Poets, Argentine -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); College teachers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Hispanic Languages and Literatures -- Faculty; University of Pittsburgh -- Faculty; Roggiano, Alfredo A.
- Conferences, Lectures, and Symposiums, 1961-1990
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I consists of conferences, lectures, and symposiums that Roggiano participated in throughout his career. Included among them are conferences at various universities nationally and abroad. Roggiano kept very detailed accounts of each lecture. The folders contain correspondences leading up to the conferences as well as programs, brochures, articles, and memorabilia related to each conference.
  - Creative Arts Week, University of Iowa, May 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Also: "Homage to Baudelaire"
  - Midwest Modern Language Association, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XII Congreso, Mexico, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Centenario del Nacimiento de Ruben Dario, Ciudad Dario, Nicaragua, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XII Congreso, Caracas, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Congreso International de Quebec, October 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XIV Congreso, Toronto, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberomericana, XVII Congreso, Madrid, May 20-26, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Separated Material
    Photographs were removed and placed in the UA Personal file.
  - Various round tables and lectures, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XIX Congreso, Pittsburgh, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ideologia, Historia, Novela, Conferencia en Yale University, March 30, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University of Massachusetts, Symposium: The Essay in the Hispanic World, May 4-5, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XX Congreso, Budapest, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Various lectures: Yale Law School, Cornell University, University of Vermont, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Louisiana Conference on Hispanic Languages and Literatures, February 26-28, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXII Congreso, Paris, France, June 13-17, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lecture, George Mason University, November 1-3, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXIII Congreso, June 25, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXIII Congreso, Madrid, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Conferences in West Germany, May 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - XI Annual Hispanic Literatures Conference, Indiana, Pennsylvania, October 11-12, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Tulane University Conference, November 14-16, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, Stanford University, California, July 8-12, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Conference on Latin American Literature, VIII Annual, Montclair State College, March 15, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - International Colloquium on Augusto Roa Bastos, Oklahoma State University, April 4-6, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - IV Simposio Internacional Sobre Literaturas Indigenas Latino Americanas, Mexico, January 4-12, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ernesto Sebato Symposium, January 22-24, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - VII Feria Internacional del Libro, Mexico, March 8-16, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Columbia University Lecture, April 3, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - International Multidisciplinary Conference on the Dominican Republic, Seton Hall University, April 10-12, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Conference at St. John's University, April 30, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Conference at the University of Minnesota, March 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Asociacion Internacional de Hispanistas, IX Congreso, Berlin, August 18-23, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXV Congreso, Universidad de Bonn, August 11-16, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lecture, Emir Rodriquez Monegal Memorial, May 1, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Louisiana Conference on Hispanic Languages and Literatures, Tulane University, February 26-28, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Union de Escritores y Artistas de Cuba, April 17-May 1, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Photographs removed and placed in the UA Personal Files under Roggiano.
  - South Eastern Conference on Latin American Studies (SECOLAS), Merida, Yucatan, April 1-5, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Congreso Internacional de Intelectuales y Artistas, Valencia, June 15-20, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Lecture, Spanish Cultural Club of Pittsburgh, May 16, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXVI Congreso, New York, June 8-12, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - IV Ibero-American Literary Colloquium, Rice University, April 7-9, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exposicion Feria Internacional de Buenos Aires, April 1988 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXVII Congreso, Mexico, August 22-26, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - IV Congreso de la Union de Escritores y Artistas de Cuba, January 24-February 3, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Latin American Indian Literatures Association (LAILA), VI International Symposium, June 13-17, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - American Comparative Literature Association, Brandeis University, March 8-11, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Symposio Internacional Hispanica Posnaniensia, May 28-June 2, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Guatemala Symposium, August 6-12, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - IV International Conference of Letras de Oro and Ideas, March 29-30, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Jornadas Internacionales Carlos Pellicer, Villahermosa, Tabasco, Mexico, February 12-16, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lecture, Pedro Henriquez Urena en Mexico, February 8, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Second Conference of the International Society for the Study of European Ideas (ISSEI), Leuven, Belgium, September 3-8, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Arizona State University, Distinguished Lecture Series, November 13-21, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Instituto Internacional de Literatura Iberoamericana, XXVIII Congreso, Brown University, June 18-21, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Professional Appointments and Activities
  Series II constitutes different facets of Roggiano's teaching career including his early appointments at the University of Tucuman, Iowa State University, the University of New Mexico, and the University of California. The folders are arranged according to place and different projects such as Roggiano's participation in teacher training groups, grant writing, departmental studies, dissertation committees, and social theatre seminars. The individual materials of each folder vary and contain bulk correspondences, among other items. Included among this series are also several files marked "otras actividades" (other activities) and "Roggiano activities." The date ranges and materials were left in the order and condition that Roggiano kept them.
  - Universidad Nacional de Tucuman, 1947-1954 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Universidad de Chile, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - The University of New Mexico and the University of California, Berkeley, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - State University of Iowa, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - State University of Iowa, 1955-57 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Otras actividades, 1958-62 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - State University of Iowa, 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - State University of Iowa, 1961-62 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Otras actividades, 1961-62 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA), Visiting Professor, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Program for Teaching Training Specialists, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Otras actividades, 1964-66 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - University of New Mexico summer session, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Social Theatre activities, University of Pittsburgh, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Trip to Los Angeles, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Roggiano activities, 1975-76 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Roggiano activities, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Distinguished Service Professor Award, University of Pittsburgh, 1982-83 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Roggiano activities, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Otras actividades, 1978-83 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Otras actividades, 1984-85 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Hispanic Department, University of Pittsburgh, History and Self-Study, May 1985 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Revista Mundi, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Rutgers University dissertation committee, April 1987 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Center for Latin American Studies, University of Pittsburgh; list of members, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Grant for the Center for Latin American Studies, University of Pittsburgh, 1987-88 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Argentina, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Nicaragua, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Donation to the National Library of Nicaragua, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - University of Cincinnati Libraries (reception for donors), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Roggiano y la Revista Iberoamericana, 1984-91 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Roggiano curriculum vitae (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Published and Unpublished Works
  Series III comprises Roggiano's poems and publications. The formats include photocopied material, articles, scholarly journals, and bound works. The publications contained within each folder vary as do the materials.
  - Poems and Publications, 1947-1989 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Main trends in Latin American literature, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Publications, 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Roggiano publications (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Poesia Argentina (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Writings (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Poems (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Poems (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Various writing, articles, manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 97-101a)
  - Prision O Transparencia, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Biography and list of publications (Box 3, Folder 103)
- Correspondences
  Series IV consists of correspondences to various people, groups, and organizations.
  - Alfonso Rangel Guerra correspondences, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - James O'Neill correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Renato Rosaldo correspondence, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Gordon R. Silber, State University of New York at Buffalo, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - University of Colorado, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Dave Halliday, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Frank Tannenbaum correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Center for Latin American Studies, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Wesley W. Posvar and Keith McDuffie sabbatical correspondence, 1976 and 1982 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Emilio Carilla correspondences, 1979, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Carmelo Mesa-Lago and Javier Herrero, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Tinker Field Research Grant Program, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Emory University correspondences, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Arlen Specter and William J. Coyne, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Ellis Island Foundation, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Montserrat Ordonez, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Teodosio Fernandez correspondences, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Stanford University, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Latin American Writer's correspondences, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Mundi correspondences, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - Universitat Regensburg, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - University of California, Carol Wall, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - Carlos Alvarez-Ude correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - Wesley W. Posvar honors convocation correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - Various correspondences (Box 3, Folder 129-131)
- Research Materials and Miscellaneous
  The last series identified as Research Materials and Miscellaneous contains folders about different individuals. These people had an impact on Roggiano's work and he kept individual folders related to them. The folders contain publications, correspondences, and a variety of other material about each individual. The dates and range of materials vary and have not been included. The folders have been arranged as Roggiano kept them. Individuals can be identified by the name on the file folders. In addition, there are several folders of miscellaneous articles and correspondence about Roggiano and the Department of Hispanic Languages and Literature.
  - Ernesto D. Marrone (Box 3, Folder 132)
  - Manuel Lopez Lorenzo (Box 3, Folder 133)
  - Graciela Maturo (Box 3, Folder 134)
  - Carlos Guido y Spano (Box 3, Folder 135-136)
  - Leopoldo Diaz (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Jose Juan Tablada (Box 3, Folder 138)
  - Federico de Onis (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Arturo Torres Rioseco (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Enrique Anderson Imbert and others (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Laureano Alban (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Jose Marti (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Ortega y Gasset (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Jaime Alazraki (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Alfonso Reyes (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Alejandra Pizarnik and others (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Baldomero Sanin Cano and Eduardo Carranza (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Jean Franco (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - Pedro Henriquez Urena (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Modernismo en Argentina (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Modernismo en Argentina (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Modernismo Roggiano (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Correspondence about Revista Iberoamericana and other articles. (Box 4, Folder 154-157)
    Includes materials on Latin American Indian Literature,
    Photographs were removed to the UA Personal File for Roggiano.
  - Twelve Golden Days Christmas poem/greeting card (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Letters from students and others, articles, etc (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Articles about Roggiano and the Department, thank you letters, etc (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - Miscellaneous articles and clippings about Roggiano and the Hispanice Department (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Original Inventory (Box 4, Folder 162)
  - Various articles in journals (Box 5)